<groups>
<group title='NWI Hierarchy Explanations'>
	<value>
		<title></title>
		<description>
			<h2>NWI Classification</h2>

			<p>The structure of the NWI classification is hierarchical, progressing from Systems and Subsystems, at the most general levels,
			to Classes, Subclasses, and Dominance Types. Modifiers for water regime, water chemistry, and soils are applied to Classes,
			Subclasses, and Dominance Types.Special modifiers describe wetlands and deepwater habitats that have been either created
			or highly modified by man or beavers.</p>
		</description>
	</value>
</group>
<group title='System'>
	<value label='Marine' value='M'>
		<pre> SYSTEM = MARINE (M): Marine, Open ocean and associated coastline </pre>

		<h2>Definition:</h2>

		<p>The Marine System describes open ocean or high-energy coastlines with salinities exceeding 30 ppt
		and little or no dilution except outside the mouths of estuaries. Shallow coastal indentations or
		bays without appreciable freshwater inflow; and coasts with exposed rocky islands,
		that provide the mainland with little or no shelter from wind and waves, are also
		considered part of the Marine system because they generally support typical marine biota.</p>

		<h2>Limits:</h2>

		<p>The Marine System extends from the outer edge of the continental shelf shoreward to one of
		three lines:

		<ol>
			<li>The landward limit of tidal inundation (extreme high water of spring tides), including the splash zone from breaking waves;</li>
			<li>The seaward limit of wetland emergents, trees, or shrubs;</li>
			<li>The seaward limit of the Estuarine System, where the limit is determined by factors other than vegetation.</li>
		</ol>
		</p>

		<h2>Description:</h2>

		<p>The distribution of plants and animals in the Marine System primarily reflects differences
		in four factors:
		
		<ol>
			<li>degree of exposure of the site to waves; </li>
			<li>texture and physicochemical nature of the substrate; </li>
			<li>amplitude of the tides; and </li>
			<li>Latitude, which governs water temperature, the intensity and duration of solar radiation, and the presence or absence of ice. </li>
		</ol>
		</p>
	</value>
	<value label='Estuarine' value='E'>
		<pre>SYSTEM = ESTUARINE (E): Estuarine (Salt marshes and brackish tidal water)</pre>

		<h2>Definition:</h2>

		<p>The Estuarine System consists of deepwater tidal habitats and adjacent tidal wetlands that
		are usually semienclosed by land but have open, partly obstructed, or sporadic access to the
		open ocean, and in which ocean water is at least occasionally diluted by freshwater runoff from
		the land. The salinity may be periodically increased above that of the open ocean by evaporation.
		Along some low-energy coastlines there is appreciable dilution of seawater. Offshore areas with
		typical estuarine plants and animals, such as red mangroves (Rhizophora mangle) and eastern
		oysters (Crassostrea virginica), are also included in the Estuarine System.</p>

		<p>The Estuarine System is defined in terms of Halinity and tidal influence. If tidal influence
		is only partially obstructed by weirs or tide (flap) gates or if tidal flux is accomplished by
		an underground connection, the area should be classified as Estuarine. However, if an area has
		been completely cut off from tidal action (e.g. totally obstructed by a dike), the area,
		regardless of its location or salinity would then fall into the Lacustrine or Palustrine Systems.</p>

		<h2>Limits:</h2>

		<p>The Estuarine System extends 

		<ol>
			<li>Upstream and landward to where ocean-derived salts measure less than 0.5% during the period
				of average annual low flow;</li>
			<li>To an imaginary line closing the mouth of a river, bay, or sound; </li>
			<li>To the seaward limit of wetland emergents, shrubs, or trees where they are not included
				in (2). The Estuarine System also includes offshore areas of continuously diluted seawater.</li>
		</ol></p>
		
		<h2>Description:</h2>

		<p>The Estuarine System includes both estuaries and lagoons. It s more strongly influenced by its
		association with land than is the Marine System. In terms of wave action, estuaries are generally
		considered to be low-energy systems. Estuarine water regimes and water chemistry are affected by
		one or more of the following forces: oceanic tides, precipitation, freshwater runoff from land areas,
		evaporation, and wind. Estuarine salinities range from hyperhaline to. The salinity may be variable,
		as in hyperhaline lagoons (e.g., Laguna Madre, Texas) and most brackish estuaries (e.g., Chesapeake
		Bay, Virginia-Maryland); or it may be relatively stable, as in sheltered euhaline embayments (e.g.,
		Chincoteague Bay, Maryland) or brackish embayments with partly obstructed access or small tidal range
		(e.g., Pamlico Sound, North Carolina).</p>

		<p>The primary data used in identifying Estuarine Systems is the salinity and plant communities
		inhabiting the areas. Lagoons that are hyperhaline are also included in the Estuarine System.
		If the mouth of an Estuarine river has been extended into the Marine System by parallel breakwater,
		the seaward limit of breakwaters forms the Estuarine/Marine break. The limit of the Estuarine System
		is further identified by the seaward limit of the wetland emergents, shrubs, or trees where these
		plants grow seaward of the line closing the mouth of a river, bay, or sound.</p>

		<p>The seaward limit of Mollusks reefs occurring outside of the line closing the mouth of a river,
		bay, or sound is also used to describe the Estuarine/Marine break. Bottom contour maps may be of
		some use in delineating the Marine/Estuarine demarcation in these instances.</p>

		<p>The location of the break separating the Estuarine System from the Tidal Riverine System can
		often be judged by identifying the upstream limit of salt tolerant vegetation. This vegetation
		change is observable on aerial photographs in many coastal areas.</p>
	</value>
	<value label='Riverine' value='R'>
		<pre>SYSTEM = RIVERINE (R) Riverine  (Rivers, creeks, and streams)</pre>

		<h2>Definition:</h2>

		<p>The Riverine System includes all wetlands and deepwater habitats contained within a channel,
		with two exceptions:

		<ol>
			<li>Wetlands dominated by trees, shrubs, persistent emergents, emergent mosses,or lichens, and </li>
			<li>habitats with water containing oceanderived salts in excess of 0.5%. </li>
		</ol>

		A channel is an open conduit either naturally or artificially created which periodically or
		continuously contains moving water, or which forms a connecting link between two bodies of standing water.
		</p>

		<h2>Limits:</h2>

		<p>The Riverine System is bounded on the landward side by upland, by the channel bank
		(including natural and man-made levees), or by wetland dominated by trees, shrubs, persistent
		emergents, emergent mosses, or lichens. In braided streams, the system is bounded by the banks
		forming the outer limits of the depression within which the braiding occurs.</p>

		<p>The Riverine System terminates at the downstream end where the concentration of ocean-derived
		salts in the water exceeds 0.5% during the period of annual average low flow, or where the channel
		enters a lake. It terminates at the upstream end where tributary streams originate, or where the
		channel leaves a lake. Springs discharging into a channel are considered part of the
		Riverine System.</p>

		<p>Where a river enters a lake, the extension of the Lacustrine shoreline across the mouth of the
		river forms the Riverine/Lacustrine break. Oxbow lakes are placed in the Palustrine or
		Lacustrine Systems unless they are connected to a Riverine System by an open channel at both ends,
		either permanently or intermittently. Ruin-of-the-river dams should be handled in the same manner
		as described above, with the Lacustrine System extending upstream to the contour approximating
		the normal spillway or pool elevation.</p>

		<h2>Description:</h2>

		<p>Water is usually, but not always, flowing in the Riverine System.
		Upland islands or Palustrine wetlands may occur in the channel, but hey are not included in the
		Riverine System. Palustrine Moss-Lichen Wetlands, Emergent Wetlands, Scrub-Shrub Wetlands,
		and Forested Wetlands may occur adjacent to the Riverine System, often on a floodplain.
		Many biologists have suggested that all the wetlands occurring on the river floodplain
		should be a part of the Riverine System because they consider their presence to be the result of
		river flooding. However, we concur with Reid and Wood (1976:72,84) who stated,
		"The floodplain is a flat expanse of land bordering an old river . . . Often the floodplain
		may take the form of a very level plain occupied by the present stream channel, and it may never,
		or only occasionally, be flooded . . . It is this subsurface water [the ground water] that controls
		to a great extent the level of lake surfaces, the flow of streams, and the extent of swamps
		and marshes."
		</p>
	</value>
</group>
<group title='Subsystem'>
</group>
<group title='Class, Subclass, and Dominance Types'>
</group>
<group title='Modifiers'>
</group>
</groups>